<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Eggington in the county of Darby concerning the right vse of things indifferent, the 3. day of August, 1596. By Symon Presse minister there.</title>
            <author>Presse, Symon, b. 1558 or 9.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1597</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09949</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20207</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102087</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837887</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837887</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2234</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09949)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2234)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1427:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Eggington in the county of Darby concerning the right vse of things indifferent, the 3. day of August, 1596. By Symon Presse minister there.</title>
                  <author>Presse, Symon, b. 1558 or 9.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Ioseph Barnes, and are to bee solde [by J. Broome, London] in Paules Church-yard at the signe of the Bible,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1597.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Bookseller's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2234:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2234:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at Eggington, in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Darby concerning the right vſe of things indifferent, the 8. Day of Auguſt, 1596.</p>
            <p>By SYMON PRESSE Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter there.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Feare God, honour the Kinge.</hi> 
               <bibl>1. <hi>Peter.</hi> 2.17.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at Oxford by Ioſeph Barnes, and are to bee ſolde in Paules Church-yard at the ſigne of the Bible. 1597.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2234:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS LOVING PARI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioners M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. F. COOKE, R. IOHN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SON, W. WALTON, R. KNIGHT, I. GYLLYVER &amp; R. SLYGH increaſe of true zeale &amp; <hi>endles felicitie.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVHen I vnderſtoode your attention in the heating of this ſermon, &amp; dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in noting certaine principall points, &amp; paines in conferring to give, penning, acquainting &amp; ſending your collections vnto many your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull friendes, &amp; at the length vnto the right honorable Sir Edmund Anderſon knight. Lord chiefe Iuſtice of the common Pleas, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent (as I geſſe) to make my ſimple ſkill liked and allowed of them, I thought it my duty to accept your endevour very kindly, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite you with procuring the ſame ſermon to be imprinted, that all men might giue you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved commendations, and note your names amongſt the number of vigilant hearers to your immoratall praiſe. Thus, not doubting of your good acceptance of the ſame, I end. Eg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gington, the 28. of Ianuarie.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, Symon Preſse.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:2234:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <hi>For if any man ſee thee that haſt knowledge, &amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
               <bibl>1. Cor. 8.10.11.12.13.</bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He occaſion of theſe woordes was this. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> as a father, had begotten the <hi>Corinthia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt, by the preachinge of the goſpel, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the ſudde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there crept in certain, who perverted the ſtraite waie of the Lorde, ſeeking to draw diſciples vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, and prevailed ſo much, that they had wonne them to the bent of their bow: for ſome woulde follow this teacher, and ſome that, wherwith many godlye men amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were ſore grieved, &amp; ſignified the ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e vnto the Apoſtle by their letters: And with al moved diuers doubts wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of one was, concerning meats ſacrificed to idoles, whervnto he anſwereth in this chapter, and in this order. Firſt, hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proveth them, that vppon an overwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning conceit of their owne knowledge, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2234:3"/>the ſame without charitie. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he declareth that the meate ſacrificed vnto Idoles, was of the number of thoſe thinges which are by nature meere in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, and of themſelues, do neither hinder nor further the ſalvation of him that vſeth them. And thirdly, he repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the raſhneſſe of them, that vſe ſuch things to the offence of others, as in this text at large is declared. The ſume wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of is thus much, that wee ought ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetely to behaue our ſelues in our chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian liberty, that wee doe not thereby offend our weake brother. The partes whereof are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> The manner how, they vſed their liberty to the offence of others. <hi>verſe. 10.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> The Apoſtles reaſons to diſſwade them from that practize. <hi>verſ. 11.12.13.</hi> which reaſons are threefold. The firſt is drawne from the hurt that is done to our brother <hi>ver. 11.</hi> The ſecond from the perſonnes, againſt whome hee ſinneth. <hi>verſ. 12.</hi> And the third hee draweth from his owne reſolution. <hi>13.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:2234:3"/>Now to the firſt part.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> The manner how they vſed their liberty to the offence of others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For if any man ſee thee that haſt knowledge.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>verſ.</hi> the <hi>10.</hi> As if hee had ſaide thus in plaine termes. There are amongſt you <hi>Corinthians,</hi> ſome, that ſo much preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e of their owne know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that without regard of their weak brethren runne into the Idoles temples, and there eate the meates that haue bene ſacrificed vnto Idols, and therby incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage them by eating to giue the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence to the Idole, which they did, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were converted vnto Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Out of theſe woordes, <hi>If any man ſee thee.</hi> Wee obſerue firſt that a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ought to be well adviſed in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctize of things indifferent, who ſeeth him, leaſt hee ſhould offend his weake brother by the want of due co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration: the reaſon whereof is this, that if hee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte this dutie, hee bringeth a curſe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on himſelfe which is to heavy for all the world to beare, as our ſaviour Chriſt forewarneth. It cannot bee avoided but
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2234:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>that offences will come, but woe bee to him by whome they come. It were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for him that a greate milſtone were hanged about his neck, and that he were caſt into the ſea, then that hee ſhould of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend one of theſe little ones. <hi>Luk. 17.1.2.</hi> Therefore it is very neceſſarie that wee ſhould regarde them that looke vppon our actions. There are <hi>2.</hi> ſorts of loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers vpon vs, <hi>1.</hi> God: <hi>2.</hi> his creatures. God, in every action looketh vpon the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the heart, in whoſe ſight nothing is good, except it bee doone in ſinceritye and obedience to his will. <hi>Deut. 12.32. 1. Sam. 16.7. Proverb. 23.26.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in regard of God, our actions are not well donne when they are well donne outwardly, but when the fountaine, I meane, the heart is pure and vncorrupt. For no ſtreame is ſweete, which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth from a ſower ſpring.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ſorte of beholders are Gods creatures. And they are either ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall, or terreſtriall. The celeſtiall are the angels, who beholde not onlye vs in earth, but alſo the face of God in heaven,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2234:4"/>
               <hi>Math. 18.10.</hi> And are ready to protect or to puniſh as execudors of his will. <hi>Pſal. 34.7. &amp; 103.20. Heb. 1.14.</hi> Which is manifeſted by <hi>Senacheribs</hi> hoſt, &amp; by the deliverance of <hi>Eliſha</hi> beſieged in <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than 2. Reg. 19.35. &amp; 6.17.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as thou oughteſt by reaſon of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell to te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>per thy tongue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> evill words, ſo oughteſt thou to bee carefull of thy ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in his ſight <hi>Eccleſ. 5.5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The terreſtriall creatures that behold vs, are either vnreſonable, or indued with reaſon. The vnreaſonable creaturs, that behold vs, ought to affray vs, leſt, as <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſſe had a mans voice give<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him to reprooue the fooliſhnes of his maiſter: ſo theſe ſhould bee produced againſt vs as witneſſes of our actions which wee haue donne in their preſence. For if it bee ſo that a man ought not to curſe the king, no not in his thought, leaſt the foules of the aire bewray him: how much more ſhould wee bee affraide, to do any thing againſt the will of our God, in the ſight of his creatures, whether ſenſles or ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, <hi>Eccleſ. 10.20.</hi> The reaſonable
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2234:5"/>creatures that behold vs on this earth, are devided by S. <hi>Paul</hi> into <hi>2.</hi> ſortes. <hi>1. Cor. 4.9.</hi> Wherof the former is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the world. The latter men. By the worlde, hee vnderſtandeth the wicked of the world: that as they liue in the world ſo they delight in and loue the ſame, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can like any thing that ſutes not to their worldly affections. Theſe men, though they can for their advantage, pretend much holineſſe, yet they intend the overthrow of religion, with the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and practize therof. Now for them no man that hath God and a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to be witneſſes of his well dooing, needs to care, but ought to go one, in the ſame whatſoever they ſay to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie as our ſaviour by his workes &amp; words hath taugh vs. <hi>Math. 15.12.13.14.</hi> The men beholders, are either weake in the faith, or ſtrong in the faith: the weake in the faith, are either ſuch as are offended with the vſing of things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, or ſuch as are offended with the refuſing of the ſame. The former ſort are ſuch as bee perſwaded, that the word
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2234:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>of God and ſacraments, are prophaned, where things of their owne nature indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, but heretofore abuſed in the time of Popery, are vſed. And theſe men had rather flie from the word, then bee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to ſee ſuch a ceremonie as the ſurples worne as by experience I knewe <hi>600.</hi> men and women flie from a ſermon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſurpleſſe was worne in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon time, ſuch men are indeede weake, for they will either haue Chriſt naked or none of him at all, not conſidering, that the kingdome of God ſtandeth not in any outward thing. <hi>Rom. 14.17, 18.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The weake of the other ſorte are they who bee ſo addicted to the ceremonies, that either they will haue them vſed or els they will not heare the word, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. Yea they are reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that the word and ſacramentes are betiered by the ceremonies and made of leſſe force without them. Theſe men muſt haue Chriſt in what garment plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth them, or they will haue none of him at all. Now what muſt a miniſter do in this caſe, ſhall hee, hand ouer head vſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2234:6"/>or refuſe the ceremonies? I trowe not. But muſt teach both theſe their weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, by declaring vnto them, that the commaunders and vrgers of ceremonies are of two ſorts, and they haue either of them a ſeverall end of their commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The one ſorte of commaunders, and vrgers are the Pope &amp; his adhere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, the end of whoſe commandement is to bynde mens conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces vnto the vſe of ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies vppon paine of da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation. Yea they will not ſtick to purſue to death ſuch as refuſe any one of their ceremonies: &amp; by this meanes many a poore wretch is driven, for feare of one wicked man, to vſe ſuch things againſt his owne conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and with the grievous offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the weake: both which are intollerable ſins, againſt himſelfe that doth the thing, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his weake brother that ſeeth the thing done, and againſt Chriſt the head of the myſticall body. Any one of which offences is ſufficient to cauſe a good chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian to reſolue with himſelfe, never to vſe the ſurpleſſe or any ſuch ceremony in ſuch a caſe. For, God forbid that ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunders
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2234:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>and vrgers of ceremonies as are the popes friends, ſhould draw a man into the danger of his owne ſoule, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as wee are taught rather to obeye God then men, <hi>Acts. 5.29.</hi> and to go forward in our calling without feare what man can do vnto vs.</p>
            <p>The other ſorte of commaunders and vrgers are chriſtian princes, and ſuch as are ſubſtituted of them, who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand and vrge ſuch things, becauſe no church government can ſtand without ſome ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies. And it is thought fit by them, that in one and the ſame region and regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, one vniforme order ſhould be vſed, which otherwiſe being left, to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of everie private ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, there would be as great varietie and alteration in ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, as there is in apparell. To prevent which diſorder, certain ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies are ſtil retained by the Queens moſt excellent maieſtie (whome God longe preſerue) not to binde mens conſciences w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> feare of da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but to traine all her ſubiects in due obedience, reſpecting this end, that according to the Apoſtles
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2234:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>doctrine, all things may bee done com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and in order. For as diſorder in the common wealth is da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous. So much more in the church of God: for thereby men are brought from ſuperſtition to no religion, a thing in theſe laſt dayes much to bee regarded. But ſome men will aſke, what if the things commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the prince, haue beene heretofore abuſed in the time of ſuperſtition, may we then vſe them with a good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience? I aunſwer yea, if the thing commaunded bee one of Gods creatures, when the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition is removed and it reſtored to the original without offence to his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience that vſeth the ſame, the people beeing taught, the indifferencie of the thing, <hi>viz,</hi> that it is not forbidden in the worde, neither by expreſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, nor by neceſſarie conſequence then it may bee vſed, without grudge or ſcruple of conſcience. As for example, the cenſors which the conſpiratours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> abuſed, were lawfully made a covering for the altar of the lorde <hi>Numb. 16.</hi> And alſo the bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2234:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>fedd. <hi>7.</hi> yeares to bee ſacrificed to <hi>Baall,</hi> was now ſacrificed to the lorde with the woode of the grove, and by the lorde accepted. For the abuſe was taken away, the thing was brought backe to his originall, and then vſed in the ſervice of the lorde, and not by him reiected. So muſt wee deale in the practiſe of thinges indifferent to cut of occaſion from them that ſeeke occaſion, that God in al things may bee glorified, the prince obeyed, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtion baniſhed, the people edified and the peace of the church preſerved. Thus ſhall the weake of neither ſorte, haue any iuſt cauſe to be offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded with our vſing of things indifferent. And thus much of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are weake in the faith.</p>
            <p>The other ſorte, namely the ſtronge in the faith, knowe the right vſe of things indifferent, aſwell as hee that v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth them him ſelfe. For as they cannot bee greeved with the vſe, ſo will they not be offended with the want of ſuch things. But when they are practiſed theſe men remember the obedience due vnto prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. And when not vſed they call to mind
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2234:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>that the woorde of God is neither bette<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by them, nor made worſe with the want of them. Where a man hath ſuch to looke vpon him, he may without ſcruple of conſcience vſe the ceremonies, to ſhew his obedience to chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> princes. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to conclude, let every man in the vſe of things indifferent meaſure his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions towards his weake brother by cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie; let his charitie proceede of fayth, and his faith abhorre the Pope, &amp; bring forth true obedience to his prince, not ſo much for feare of puniſhment, as for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake. So ſhall hee neither of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his brother, his prince, nor his God. And then needeth hee not to care who ſeeth him, to practiſe things indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent. And thus much of the firſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If any man ſee thee.</hi> &amp;c. In theſe words againe our Apoſtle covertlie giveth a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veat to every ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to take heed to his eies, leſt by them hee bee unboldened to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itate ſuch thinges as are wrought in his ſight. From whence wee learne, that ſinne entereth into our ſouls by our
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2234:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>eies as light into an houſe by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> window: for the eie vieweth the obiect, and ſendes it by degrees into the heart; the hart po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth vpon the report, yeeldeth conſent, and ſetteth the eie on worke to performe the harts deſire. And hereof it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our ſaviour Chriſt ſayth, a wicked eye mommeth out of the hart, and defileth the man. <hi>Mark. 7.22.</hi> Yea and proceedeth further, affirming that he who looketh v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon a woman and luſteth after her, hath committed adulterie alreadie with her in his hearie. <hi>Math. 5.28.</hi> Herevppon David maketh this earneſt praier, turne away mine eies, O lord, from regarding vanitie. <hi>Pſal. 119.37.</hi> Wherefore it is good for vs, rather then thus to offend by them, to plucke them out and caſt them from vs, <hi>Math. 18.9.</hi> which courſe if our greate grandmother <hi>Hevah</hi> had taken, when ſhee looked vpon the apple, ſhe had not ſo ſoone yeelded vnto ſathan, neither intiſed her huſband to doe the like, nor inwrapped mankinde in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnſufferable, and yet vnavoidable curſe of God, <hi>Gen. 3.6.</hi> The ſonnes of God that behelde the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2234:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>bewty of the daughters of men and choſe them wiues by ſight, not by vertue were a great cauſe of the general deluge. <hi>Gen. 6.2. David</hi> had litle ioy a greate while of that ſight of <hi>Bathſheba.</hi> His ſweete meate had very ſower ſauce, <hi>2. Sam. 11.</hi> &amp; <hi>12. <hi>per totum.</hi>
               </hi> Wherefore let everye man bee admoniſhed with <hi>Iob</hi> to make a covenaunt with his eyes, not to looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any vnlawfull thing. And if hee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not rule them, let him plucke them oute that they may not bee an impediment to his ſoule. And thus much of this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde obſervation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That haſt knowledge &amp;c.</hi> The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle here noteth that men of knowledge may abuſe the ſame to the hurt of others and ſo make that exellent quality hurtful to them ſelues, and to them with whom they converſe. From whence this obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation naturally ariſeth, that, that which is commanded in the ſubſtance, may be made ſinne in the circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtance. For God will haue all our actions to bee ſuitable to his will, both in matter and forme, otherwiſe they are not good in his ſight.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2234:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>For it is not enough to doe that which he commandeth except we doe it as he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth the ſame to bee done. <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Aaron</hi> are commended, not only for obſerving the commaundement, but alſo becauſe that as the lord comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> &amp; <hi>Aaron,</hi> even ſo did they, <hi>Exod. 7.6.</hi> Our ſaviour Chriſt (when hee had waſhed his diſciples feete) biddeth them, not only to doe that which hee had doone, but alſo as hee had done, <hi>Iohn. 13.14.15.</hi> For as well the forme as the matter muſt concurr in everie action. Wherfore if you marke it, you ſhall perceiue that every thing hath his limitation. Out of which compaſſe vertue is turned into vice, as for example alms deeds, praier &amp; faſting, are commaunded and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by Chriſt Ieſus, yet may they bee wrought &amp; not be acceptable vnto God, as our ſavior manifeſtly declareth, <hi>Mat. 6.</hi> from the <hi>1.</hi> verſe vnto the <hi>18.</hi> for there we may ſee, that if he who giveth almes, cauſe a trumpet to be blown before him, or deſire to bee ſeene of men, or to bee praiſed of them, hee is gone out of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2234:10"/>compaſſe and hath loſt his reward. Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is commended likewiſe and the forme thereof ſet downe: but hee that praieth, muſt not run into the ſtreetes and open places to bee viewed and prayſed of men, neither may hee vſe vaine repetitions, as the papiſts, nor much babling as the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then. Faſting alſo is a preparatiue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to many vertues, but yet a man may nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther looke ſower, nor diſfigure his face to bee ſeene of men, nor thinke to make God indebted vnto him for his faſting, as though hee had neede of it. Knowledge in like ſorte is commanded in the ſcip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and wee are commanded to cal af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter knowledge, to cry for vnderſtanding, to ſeeke for it as for ſilver, and to ſearch for it as for treaſures, <hi>Pro. 2.3.4.</hi> yea and to account our ſelues happye when wee finde it, for ignorance is very hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto God and hurtfull vnto me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Yet for all that, knowledge muſt keepe her ſelfe within her bonds, ſhe muſt not puffe him vp that poſſeſſeth her, ſhe muſt haue charitie her companion and guide. And howſoever ſhe may ſhew her ſelfe in her
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2234:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>dime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſions vnto her acquaintance, yet vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſtrangers, that is, the ignorant, ſhee muſt make her ſelfe knowne by little and litle, as they are able to receiue her to their edification, and not to their deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For ſhe muſt bee to the ignorant as milke to babes. To the weake, as hearbes to ſickly ſtomackes, and to the ſtrong as ſtronge meate for men. And to evry one as they are able to abide her, that at the length, by her they may bee wonne vnto the lorde. For haue her they muſt in ſome meaſure, or els heaven will bee not habitation for them. For knowledge is the mother and daughter of faith. And is ſo aſſociated vnto faith, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> none can be ſaved but ſuch as beleeue and come to the knowledge of the truth. <hi>1. Tim. 2.4.1. Pet. 1.9.</hi> And what ſhould I ſay more, the caſe is clear. Whatſoever thou doſt, be it neuer ſo good in ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; yet maiſt thou marre it in circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Be it neuer ſo holy in the matter, yet maiſt thou ſo ſoile it in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maner of doing, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the lord may iuſtly aborre it, though he haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded thee to doe it, becauſe it is not
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2234:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>done as hee commandeth. And thus much of the third obſervation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sit at table in the Idols temple.</hi> Our Apoſtle woulde haue the Idolatrous place and perſons auoided, as where and among whome no good can bee gotten to a mans ſelfe and much evill may bee ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected to come thereby. For often it commeth to paſſe, that with whom wee converſe familiarly in worldely thinges, by him wee are drawne, either from our profeſſion, or from the former zeale, wee were wont to haue there in, beſides the corruption of our maners. Wherby we are taught this neceſſarie leſſon, to be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious of the place and company we keep, leſt wee corrupt our fayth and defile our maners. For hee that toucheth pitch ſhal be defiled there with, which the lorde foreſaw and therefore made this procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation by the prophet, departe, departe ye, goe out from thence, and touch noe vncleane thing, goe out of the mideſt of her, bee cleane yee that carrie the veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of the lord, <hi>Iſa. 52.11.</hi> And this cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed our Apoſtle to vrge a ſeperation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2234:11"/>the godly and vngodly. <hi>2. Cor. 6.14.15. Lot</hi> muſt packe out of <hi>Sodome Gen. 19.17.</hi> The congregation of the Lord muſt ſeperate themſelues from the tents of <hi>Corah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abiron, Numb. 16.26. Iehoſhaphat</hi> is won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at by the prophet, that he wil helpe the wicked and like their company that hate the lorde. <hi>2. Paral. 19.2.</hi> what doth all this teach vs, but that wee ought to bee curious with whom wee keepe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, leſt thereby wee not only hurt our ſelues but offend the Lorde. But ſome men will ſay, doe yee abſolutely conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne accompanying with the wicked? I aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer no. For as a Phiſition may bee in the companye of the ſicke, having this end to heale them, ſo may a good man bee in the aſſembly of the wicked, having this purpoſe to win them vnto the Lord. So Chriſt kept company with the publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans and ſinners, not allowing of their life, but perſwading them to amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And when hee was carped at by the malitious, hee defended his dooings by three arguments. The firſt drawne
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2234:12"/>from the neede y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the parties had of him with whom hee converſed. The ſeconde hee drewe from the diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the lord, who is more delighted with mercy ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the converſion of a ſinner then with all other ſacrifices. And the third argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hee draweth from the end of his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, which was to call ſinners to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. <hi>Math 9.12.13.</hi> Wherefore in ſuch caſes wee may lawfully keepe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with ſinners, without hurt vnto our ſelues, and with much profit vnto them. Otherwiſe wee ought to obſerue the gene<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rall doctrine to bee curious of the place and perſons with whome wee keepe company, leſt we hurt our ſelues and doo them no good. And thus much of the fourth obſervation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shall not the conſcience of him that is weake bee boldened to eate,</hi> &amp;c. Our Apoſtle foreſeeing that ſmall offences woulde grieue and perplex the weake, admoniſheth the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to haue a ſpecial regard not to trouble ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces with the abuſing of their knowledge. Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence we learne, that ſuch as make
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2234:12"/>conſcience of every thing which they do, muſt circumſpectly bee dealt with, leſt they bee led out of the way, or bee dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to diſpaire by a matter of it ſelfe of ſmall importance. For there are ſome that yeeld the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues ſo humbly vnto the word preached, that when any thing is denounced, their harte melteth &amp; their fleſh trembleth. And though it bee not applyed by the preacher, yet they apply it very ſtrictly vnto them ſelues. And if any fault whereof they are guilty be am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plified, or a comfort not preſently mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, they are in the horrors of death, &amp; brought almoſt into deſperation. Now becauſe theſe are the beſt people, and the neareſt to the kingdome of God, <hi>Pſal. 51.17. Iſa. 66.2. Math. 11.28.</hi> We ought to bee moſt carefull of them, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue all ſtumbling blockes out of their way. As for example, if they haue a great zeale but not according to knowledg we muſt gently and charitably inſtruct them without wrangling diſputations: As wee are taught, him that is weake in the fayth receiue vnto you: but not with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2234:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>of diſputations, <hi>Rom. 14.1.</hi> And if hee, (by the ſubtlety of Sathan) bee prevented with a fault (as who is free from falling) we muſt not aggravate or amplify the ſame, but follow that rule which the holy ghoſt teacheth. Brethren, if a man bee fallen by occaſion into anye fault, yee which are ſpirituall, reſtore ſuch a one by the ſpirit of meekenes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering thy ſelfe, leſt thou alſo be temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Beare yee one an others burthen &amp; ſo fulfill the lawe of Chriſt, <hi>Gal. 6.1.2.</hi> Wee which are ſtrong, ought to beare the infirmities of the weake, and not to pleaſe our ſelues, <hi>Rom. 15.1.</hi> For if it bee <hi>David</hi> that hath ſinned, tell him but of it, and hee will confeſſe it, and be woe at the heart for it, thou needeſt not to dwell much vpon it. And if it be <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> that hath donne amiſſe, let Chriſt but lacke backe vpon him, hee will goe out forthwith and weepe bitterly. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch tender conſciences, muſt choiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bee dealt withall, leſt they be ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vp of over much ſorrowe. And thus much of the fift obſervation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:2234:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Thoſe things that are offered vnto Idoles.</hi> Our Apoſtle in theſe wordes maketh it evident, that there is a <hi>2.</hi> fold eating of that which is ſacrificed vnto I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols. For one man hath knowledge, and thereby is inſtructed, that the meate which hee eateth hath beene ſacrificed to Idoles, yet is neither bettered nor made worſe thereby. An other man that wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth knowledge, maketh conſcience of the meate and thinketh that it is much bettered by the ſacrificing, and ſo his conſcience being weake is defiled. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle reſtraineth the former from vſing his liberty, vntill the latter be further inſtructed, in the right vſe of ſuch things. From whence we may draw this doctrine: that a man, who either hath or wanteth knowledge, may by the vndiſcreete cariage of himſelfe, in the vſe of things indifferent, make that ſinne, which God hath neither commanded nor forbidden in his worde. Hee that hath knowledge may ſinne one way, that is, by vſing his liberty, to the offence of an other chriſtian that is weake. Vnto him
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2234:14"/>therefore, it muſt often be inculcated, deſtroy not the worke of God for meate-ſake. All things indeede are pure, but it is evil for the man that eateth with of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. It is good neither to eate fleſhe nor to drinke wine, nor any thing whereby thy brother ſtumbleth or is offended or made weake, <hi>Rom. 14.20.21.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he offendeth God, that wittingly and willingly giveth offence vnto the weake, by the vſing of things indifferent. Now he that wanteth knowledge may offende in the vſe of thinges indifferent three waies.</p>
            <p>Firſt, if he vſe the ſame vnto an other end the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for which it was ordained of God. As if a man vſe this meate &amp; refuſe that, vſe this garment, and refuſe that, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king therby to pleaſe God, he indeede ſinneth againſt him. For hee muſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that the kingdom of God is not meate and drinke; but righteouſneſſe &amp; peace, &amp; ioy in the holy ghoſt. For who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer in theſe things ſerveth Chriſt, is acceptable vnto God and approved of men. <hi>Rom. 14.17.18.</hi> For every crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2234:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>of God is good and none to be refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, if it bee received with giuing of thankes. <hi>1. Tim. 4.4.</hi> Wherefore he that inventeth an holyer vſe of Gods crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures then that wherunto they were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, doth as it were ſet God to ſchoole than which, what can be more malapart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly done. <hi>Iſa. 40.13.14.</hi> ſecondly they that want knowledge may offende in the vſe of things indifferent thus: as if they haue a reſolute opinion, that the vſe of ſuch things offendeth God, and yet will goe on in the practiſe thereof, againſt their owne conſcience, they indeede, grevouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offend againſt God. For to him that iudgeth any thing to be vncleane, to him it is vncleane, <hi>Rom. 14.14.</hi> And if a mans owne conſcience condemne him of diſobedience, who can abſolue him, <hi>1. Io. 3.20.</hi> And thirdly hee that wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth knowledge, may offend his God thus, when hee propoſeth a thing by himſelfe to bee done, and doubteth whether hee ſhall doe well or ill in the doing of the ſame, yet for ſome outward reſpect hee puts the ſame thing in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2234:15"/>For hee that doubteth is condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned if hee eate, becauſe hee eateth not of fayth. And whatſoever is not of faith is ſinne. <hi>Rom. 14.23.</hi> Therefore in the name of Chriſt Ieſus, let both ſtrong and weake looke warely to their actions, that they offend neither God, their weake bretheren, nor their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences. And thus much of the firſt parte.</p>
            <p>The ſecond part contayneth the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to mooue men to bee circumſpect in the cariage of themſelues in the matter of things indifferent. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the firſt is this that hee that omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth this dutie ſhall cauſe him to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh for whome Chriſt died, <hi>verſe 11.</hi> the ſecond extendeth it ſelfe vnto the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting of Chriſt Ieſus for whatſoever is donne vnto any one of his church, he taketh as donne vnto himſelfe, <hi>verſ. 12.</hi> And laſt of all hee that omitteth this duty oppoſeth himſelfe againſt <hi>Pauls</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution who was guided by the ſpirit of God. And thus much at this time. Let vs pray &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
